<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The faithful covenanter. A sermon preached at the lecture in Dedham in Essex. By that excellent servant of Iesus Christ, in the work of the Gospel, Mr. Tho. Hooker, late of Chelmsford; now in New England. Very usefull in these times of covenanting with God.</title>
            <author>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86526</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2648</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E81_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15313</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859838</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859838</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111937</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86526)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111937)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 14:E81[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The faithful covenanter. A sermon preached at the lecture in Dedham in Essex. By that excellent servant of Iesus Christ, in the work of the Gospel, Mr. Tho. Hooker, late of Chelmsford; now in New England. Very usefull in these times of covenanting with God.</title>
                  <author>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Christopher Meredith at the Crane in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: The last 4 in the imprint date is crossed out; "Jan: 10th 1643".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Deuteronomy XXIX, 24-25 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111937:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111937:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FAITHFUL COVENANTER.</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT THE LECTVRE IN <hi>DEDHAM</hi> IN <hi>ESSEX.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By that excellent ſervant of Ieſus Chriſt, in the work of the Goſpel, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Tho. Hooker,</hi> late of <hi>Chelmsford;</hi> now in New <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Very uſefull in theſe times of Covenanting with God.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal 78. verſ. 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The children of Ephraim being armed, and carying Bows, turned back in the day of Battle.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ver. 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>They kept not the Covenant of God: and refuſed to walk in his Law.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ver. 36.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Nevertheleſſe, they did flatter him with their mouth: and they lied unto him with their tongues.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Verſ. 37.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For their heart was not right with him: neither were they ſtedfaſt in his Covenant.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for CHRISTOPHER MEREDITH at the Crane in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:111937:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111937:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED AT <hi>DEDHAM</hi> Lecture in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>DEUT. 29.24, 25.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Even all Nations ſhall ſay, Wherefore hath the Lord done thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this land? what meaneth the heate of this great anger?</p>
                  <p>Then the men ſhall ſay, Becauſe they have forſaken the Covenant of the Lord God of their fathers, which he made with them when he brought them forth out of the land of Egypt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy Prophet <hi>Moſes,</hi> having in the fore-going Chapters, the 28. eſpecially, diſcovered unto the people as his laſt words al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt which he ſpake unto them, the marvellous mercies of the Lord to thoſe which walked with him, and were obedient unto his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111937:3"/>which he had ſet before them, and the heavy Iudgements he had prepared for, and would execute on them that walked ſtubbornly againſt him; and were diſobedient and rebellious, notwithſtanding all meanes he uſed to reclaime them, and all the bleſſings that he beſtowed upon them, as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements you may ſee in the fore-going Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>If you will obſerve and doe all that I command you this day:</hi> verſ. 1. then verſ. 3. <hi>Bleſſed ſhalt thou be in the Citie, and bleſſed ſhalt thou be in the field:</hi> verſ. 4. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall be the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy ground:</hi> verſ. 5. <hi>Bleſſed ſhall be thy basket and thy ſtore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if not, but they will be diſobedient and rebell againſt him, he ſends fire after them preſently, and ſayes, verſ. 16. <hi>Curſed ſhalt thou be in the Citie, and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhalt thou be in the field.</hi> verſ. 17. <hi>Curſed ſhalt thou be in thy basket, and in thy ſtore, &amp;c.</hi> Now having dealt with them both waies, he windes up all, and deales with them by way of Prophecie, and tels them, what <hi>Iſrael</hi> would doe, and what the Lord would doe, if their hearts turned away from him, and from his Statutes, which he had ſet before them to walke in. He tels them that the people after his death will goe a whoring, <hi>O that this might not be,</hi> ſayes <hi>Moſes,</hi> but yet if it be, the Lord will roote you out of this good Land, and will bring upon you <hi>all theſe curſes that are written in this Booke,</hi> to plague you here, and will cauſe everlaſting vengeance to ſeiſe upon you here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>Now after he had dealt with them by mercies and judgements, theſe not prevailing, the Lord ſends an enemie upon them that ſweepes them away as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable<note n="*" place="margin">1 King 14.10. a King. 9 37. Pſal. 83.10. Ier. 8.2. &amp; 9.22 &amp; 16.4. &amp; 25.33.</note> dung off the face of the earth. Now the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111937:3"/>Prophet brings in the Nations here juſtifying the Lords dealing with them, and ſaying, verſ. 24. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath the Lord done thus unto this Land?</hi> What meaneth this fierce wrath of the Lord?</p>
            <p>As if a man ſhould ſay, What was this goodly ENGLAND, the onely Nation of all the Earth, and yet now all laid waſte in this fearefull manner? Whence came this heavie diſpleaſure, and what doth meane this fierce wrath of the Lord? Now marke what followes, <hi>All men ſhall ſay,</hi> that is, <hi>even the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked themſelves,</hi> all ſtanders by ſhall give ſentence on the Lords ſide, and juſtifie his doings, and ſay, Alas, can you blame the Lord for dealing thus fiercely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch a ſtubborne rebellious people? What would you have had the Lord done more, he gave them a Law, and Mercies, and Iudgements, but they would not ſerve the Lord, but brake the bands aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>and caſt the cords behinde their backs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.3.</note> Therefore now they ſhall ſerve enemies. God is not to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, What could he have done, or what would you have had him doe more then he did for them? Threatnings from Mount <hi>Eball,</hi> and Bleſſings from Mount <hi>Gerizzim</hi> flue about from this ſide, and on that ſide, and yet nothing would doe them good: Why ſhould they live any longer then? what ſhould the Lord doe? they profited by nothing, neither by his mercies, nor his judgements; and what was the cauſe, brethren? Here was the cauſe, they were falſe hearted, they would not walke ſincerely with the Lord; and therefore the anger of the Lord was kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt them, and he rootetd them out of their Land in his wrath, and in great indignation. Oh the fearefull wrath of the Lord that came upon them!</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:111937:4"/>
            <p>In the words take notice of three particulars:<note place="margin">Parts of the Text.</note> Firſt, the Iudgement of the Lord denounced, threatned <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and executed againſt them. It was very ſharpe, the Nations were agaſt that ſtood by and beheld it, and wondred, and ſaid, Why, who would have thought it, that the adverſary and the enemy ſhould have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the gates of <hi>Ieruſalem?</hi> What, <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the perfection of beauty, <hi>the joy of the whole Earth?</hi> As if one ſhould hereafter paſſe by and ſee all the Townes burnt up here in this Land, (which God grant may never be) but if it ſhould be ſo, and one ſhould paſſe by and ſee all the houſes burnt up, and the Churches burnt; would he not be amazed at it, and ſay, Why, what meanes this fierce wrath of the Lord? Would it not make our hearts ake Brethren, to paſſe by theſe places, and ſee the houſes of God burnt downe to the ground, and thinke with our ſelves; Oh the good exhortations and admonitions we have heard here!</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Then ſecondly, here is the reaſon and cauſe why the Lord dealt thus with them,<note place="margin">Verſ. 25.</note> 
               <hi>then men ſhall ſay, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have forſaken the Covenant of the Lord their God.</hi> So brethren, if this ſhould be our caſe, poore little ones would ſay then, I remember my father ſaid thus it would be, for the Land forſooke the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Lord; and the Miniſter told us of this ſtubbornneſſe and rebellion againſt the Lord, that this would be the end of it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Then laſtly, here is the teſtimony of the Nations concerning the equitie of the Lords dealing; the ſtanders by juſtifie it, and ſaid, The Lord is juſt, for they have forſaken the Covenant of the Lord their God.</p>
            <p>And ſo people would doe here if the Lord ſhould
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111937:4"/>doe with us as he did with the Jews. Firſt, of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> judgements which the Lord threatned againſt them. <hi>What means the fierce anger of the Lord?</hi> why, it was the fierce anger of the enemies, was it not? Yes, But there is no enemy but is in Gods hand, it is his wrath that they execute. The wicked of the world are but the Lords inſtruments; the Sword is thine Lord, though thou uſeſt them as the hand to ſtrike with. The Lord commanded deſtruction to come upon them;<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hence obſerve God is the Author of all thoſe puniſhments and judgements, that ever come upon a nation or people, fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or perſon.</hi> It is his will that is the worker; He is the bringer of all ſorrows, troubles, and judgements upon any. It was not the <hi>Babylonians</hi> that overthrew them; It was not <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> it was the fierce anger of the Lord that did it: you know what God himſelfe ſayes, <hi>Is there any evill in the citie, and I have not done it? Amos</hi> 3.6. <hi>And he hiſſe for an enemy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 4 5.7.</note> all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are at his command,<note place="margin">Iſa. 7.18.</note> he commands deliverance for them, that ſerve and obey him, as it is in the <hi>Pſalm:</hi> and plagues and deſtruction for them that diſobey him, and rebell againſt him.</p>
            <p>To make this then our own, brethren, by applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, briefly, for I meane to faſten upon nothing in this verſe, but to paſſe on to the other wherein is contained the maine point which I intend to ſtand upon, as thinking it in my thoughts moſt fit for this congregation. If this be ſo, then here is a cooling card for the wicked.<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> All you that heare this word this day, whoſe conſciences accuſe you, that you are enemies to God and goodneſſe, heare and feare, and tremble for ever; If God bring judgements, who ſhall feele them and finde them? ſurely, his enemies
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111937:5"/>be them that ſhall feele them,<note place="margin">Pſal. 10 16.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.16. It is the collection that the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> makes. <hi>The Lord is King for ever,</hi> and what then? <hi>the heathen are deſtroyed,</hi> ſayes he. If all judgements be at his command, then his enemies ſhall be ſure to feele them. You that have wicked husbands or wives, feare every night when you goe to bed, leſt the judgement of the Lord ſhould come upon them, yet ere morning, and cut them off and ſend them to deſtruction.<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> And you that are careleſſe of your wayes, and goe on in your wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, underſtand the Lord hath vengeance for you; He hath rods enough, they are not all burnt, he will bring them our againſt you,<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.21.</note> 
               <hi>and will wound the hairie ſcalpe of him that goeth on in his ſins.</hi> Marke what the Apoſtle ſaies,<note place="margin">1 Pet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.18.</note> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.18. <hi>If the righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall the ungodly and the ſinner appeare.</hi> If the righteous (brethren) hardly get to heaven, but loſes an arme, an other a right eye as it were, and with many prayers, and ſighes, and graplings with God, and through many temptations hardly come to heaven in the end, and a poore humble ſoule begge for power againſt his corruptions, as if he would pluck mercy from the Lord by ſtrong hand, and yet ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubdue ſinne and obtaine ſalvation; what then will become of a company that are enemies to God and godlines, a company of unrighteous men, where ſhall they appeare; The day will come when they that ſtand againſt the gracious voyce of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie now, ſhall heare the thundering voyce of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.30.</note> and ſhall call and cry <hi>to the mountaines and hills to fall upon them and cover them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 6.16.</note> that they may be hid from the preſence of the Judge.</p>
            <p>Secondly, obſerve that the Text ſayes, <hi>What means
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111937:5"/>the fierce anger of the Lord againſt this nation?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 19 5. Tit. 2.14. 1 Pet. 2 9. Pſal. 60 5. and 108.6. and 127.2. Rom. 3.2.</note> What nation? why, the nation of the Jews, Gods owne peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, his * peculiar, <hi>his firſt borne,</hi> Exod. 4.22. <hi>his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved,</hi> Cant. 1.14, 15. and 5.1, 2. <hi>to whom the</hi> oracles of God were committed, to whom the Prophets came in his name. That nation that had all means of good, that had all mercies, priviledges, and all encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Lord ſhewed his fierce wrath to them. Learne:<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>No outward priviledges in the world will free any nation under heaven from the judgements of the Lord, if they ſinne againſt him, and be ſtubborn and rebellious.</hi> If any people might have been exempted and freed, ſurely the Jews might; They might have ſaid, Why Lord wilt thou plague us? what, wilt thou deſtroy us? why, we are thy people, we have thy ſacrifices, and thy Prophets, and thy Temple is amongſt us. That is all one, what <hi>means the fierce anger of the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this nation? ſayes the Text.</hi> Be the man what he will, the means never ſo excellent, and the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges never ſo great, if he ſin, he ſhall be ſure to be plagued, <hi>Ier.</hi> 7.12. Brethren you may ſee there, that when the Prophet threatned the judgements of the Lord againſt them; Jeruſalem began to brag of her priviledges, and the mercies of God which he had beſtowed on them; <hi>Go to Shiloh, ſayes the Lord to them, the place where I ſet my name at firſt, and ſee what I did to it, for the wickedneſſe of my people Iſrael.</hi> The caſe is cleare and plaine, no priviledges, though the word of God and his ordinances, and the meanes of grace be there, will keepe away judgements: If people ſin, God will proceed in wrath againſt them, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.2. <hi>You only have I knowne (ſayes the Lord) of all the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the earth:</hi> what then? therefore will I cocker
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111937:6"/>and dandle you? no, but <hi>therefore will I viſit you for all your iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this be ſo brethren,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> this teaches us this inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>Not to depend upon our priviledges, not to boaſt of them, and reſt in them,</hi> and go away, and ſay, What, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> come into <hi>England!</hi> what, the enemy over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>England!</hi> We have the Goſpel, the meanes of Grace, no nation under heaven ſo many in it that feare the Lord as our nation hath. O truſt not toly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vanities,<note place="margin">Jonas 2.8.</note> ſaying, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 7.4.</note> as the Jews did when the <hi>Babylonian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> came: what good did their Temple doe them? your outward profeſſion will be your bane if you truſt to it,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.9.</note> when time of trouble come; <hi>Tribulation and anguiſh ſhall be upon every ſoul that ſins, upon the Iew firſt,</hi> marke that brethren; The higheſt in preferment, the firſt in puniſhment: you that have enjoyed great meanes, the Lord will proceed more heavily againſt you, then againſt others, when he begins to execute his wrath once; To have the name of outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is nothing, it will leave us in the duſt if we truſt to it: Priviledges are like to paper walles, if a man reare up a paper wall againſt Cannon ſhot, will that defend, him brethren? They are good in their place and kinde, but if we put our confidence in them, as if they ſhould keepe us out of trouble, it is like as if a man ſhould put on a cut Sattin ſuit, or coat of ſilke to goe in the warres withall, will that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve him againſt the Cannons, and the enemies? your outward appearance of profeſſion is juſt ſo brethren. A hypocriticall, fine ſmooth coat will not keep off the wrath of the Lord, but that will ſeiſe upon the ſoule, which hath no other defence but ſuch.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:111937:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Revelation</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Revel. 2.2.</note> and the beginning <hi>Epheſus</hi> a Church that lived gloriouſly, and performed duties comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, marke what the Lord ſayes of them,<note place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note> 
               <hi>I know thy works and thy labour, and how thou canſt not beare them which are evill,</hi> verſ. 4. <hi>Yet I have ſomewhat againſt thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 4.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe thou haſt left thy firſt love.</hi> And what of that, might ſome ſay, I may be an honeſt man I hope, and goe to heaven too, though I have declined a little, and be not ſo zealous and forward as I have been, as long as I am ſincere and upright-hearted. Aye, but what ſayes the Lord, brethren;<note place="margin">Verſ. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Remember from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and doe thy firſt works, or elſe I will come unto thee quickly, and remove thy Candleſticke out of his place.</hi> Let no man truſt in his own ſtrength, depend upon his own priviledges, and ſhadow him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe under the name of Religion, and Goſpel.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 4 5, 6.</note> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. When the Philiſtines came againſt Iſrael, and Iſrael was ſmitten before them, the next time they came into the Campe, they ſent for the Arke that that might ſave them out of the hand of their enemies, and when the Arke came into the Campe,<note place="margin">Verſ. 5.</note> 
               <hi>all Iſrael ſhouted, ſo that the earth rang again.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 7.</note> 
               <hi>And the Philiſtines were afraid and ſaid, Woe unto us, for the like was never heard of before, the God of Iſrael is come into the Field. Who ſhall deliver us out of the hands of theſe mightie Gods?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 8.</note> 
               <hi>theſe are the Gods that ſmote the Egyptians with all the plagues that came upon them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Be ſtrong and quit your ſelves like men, oh ye Philiſtines, that ye be not ſervants unto the Hebrews. And the Philiſtines fought,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> 
               <hi>and Iſrael was ſmitten. And the Arke of God was taken.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 11.</note> They brought the Arke of the Covenant into the Campe, but the Arke would not defend them, but was taken; Brethren, the Arke was a type of Chriſt, you bring
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111937:7"/>the name of Chriſtians, and the outward profeſſion of Religion into the field, and you thinke that this will ſave you out of the hands of your enemies, but you and that will ſinke under your enemies, if you put confidence in that: was any nation greater then Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, or more glorious then Jeruſalem? but what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of them brethren? hath not the Lord brought deſolation and deſtruction upon them?<note place="margin">Luk. 21.5.</note> 
               <hi>O ſay the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> (when they were at Jeruſalem and ſaw the Temple) <hi>what goodly buildings are here!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 24.1, 2.</note> verſ. 2.<note place="margin">Mark. 13.1, 2.</note> I tell you ſays our Saviour, <hi>a ſtone ſhall not be left on a ſtone;</hi> It skils not what we are, brethren, in outward profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but what we are in ſinceritie, and holineſſe. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend not on the priviledges which God hath given you, but pray for grace to anſwer him, according to the means which he hath beſtowed upon you, and then this love may be continued, and there may be ſome hope that you ſhall injoy theſe bleſſed privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges ſtill.</p>
            <p>Now we come to the place where we would be, the 25.<note place="margin">Verſ. 25.</note> 
               <hi>verſe,</hi> wherein is the reaſon why God deals ſo with his own people.</p>
            <p>The Text gives you to underſtand the ground of it was becauſe they had forſooke the Covenant of their God.<note place="margin">Meaning of the words.</note> This we will faſten upon. And firſt I will open the words, and then draw ſome collections from them for our benefit.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I will ſhew you what is meant by Covenant. Secondly, what is meant by forſaking of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Brethren,<note place="margin">Covenant.</note> there is a double Covenant in the frame <hi>of Scripture.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 3.15, 16. and 5.24. and 11.25, 26.</note> Firſt, a Covenant of being in God, which is called the Covenant of faith. <hi>He that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth ſhall live.</hi> Secondly, a Covenant <hi>of walking be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> or with God, when we have received mercy and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111937:7"/>grace through the goodneſſe of God in acceptation of our perſons, in and through Chriſt, then the Lord requires that we ſhould walke in new obedience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, anſwerable to that grace beſtowed; Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren marke that; and this is the covenant of new o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience or of thankfulneſſe, which the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals, requires, and exacts of all that have given their names unto him. I take it that the covenant of the ſecond ſenſe is here meant; The other is ſuppoſed and included, but this is the maine, the covenant of his Law, whereby we ſhould be obedient unto him, that is the minde of the holy man in this place, and the ſcope of the words.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to forſake this covenant is this; when we keepe not touch with God, in ſincere, exact, and holy obedience, anſwerable to the means and mercy he beſtows upon us, and the care and kindneſſe of the Lord towards us. When we fleeing away from the command of the Lord, breake his bands,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.3.</note> and ſnap the cords a pieces, when we walke after our own wayes, are not governed by God, and content to be ruled by his holy word in all things, then are we ſaid to forſake his covenant. Nextly marke here, he ſayes, <hi>they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke it,</hi> that is, the generall frame of the nation. The generall, not the naughtie packs only and ſome few, but <hi>they</hi> forſooke it.</p>
            <p>Now brethren having opened the words unto you, I will come unto the points of inſtruction; and firſt in that he cals his Commandement, and Law his Covenant, obſerve a maine point of great uſe and benefit, and that is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Commandements of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doctrine.</note> 
               <hi>are the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Lord with his people, the Covenant of new obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience:</hi> This is the Covenant that God makes with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111937:8"/>his people,<note place="margin">Deut. 5.2.6.</note> not of life, but of thankfulneſſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.2.6. That one place will caſt the caſe cleere enough. In the ſecond <hi>verſ.</hi> he ſaith, <hi>The Lord our God made a Covenant with us in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oreh;</hi> then in the ſixt <hi>verſ.</hi> and ſo on,<note place="margin">Verſ 6.</note> there is the Covenant it ſelfe ſet downe. <hi>I am the Lord thy God which brought thee out of the Land of Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 7.</note> 
               <hi>out of the houſe of bondage. Thou ſhalt have none other Gods before me.</hi> Famous is that place, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.18.<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.17, 18</note> There are two Phraſes uſed which ſerve to one purpoſe, and the one explicates the other, <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>The goodneſſe of the Lord indures for ever and ever;</hi> But upon whom,<note place="margin">Verſ. 18.</note> brethren? <hi>upon thoſe that keepe his Commandements, and thinke upon his Covenants to doe them.</hi> So that his Covenants and Commandements are all one. As in a Covenant there are Articles of agreement betweene party and party; ſo betweene God and his people. Here are the Articles of agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Ten words which God ſpake, the Ten Commandements: This <hi>Moſes</hi> aimes at here: Now brethren, to ſet the truth upon his right ground, for the opening of the point take notice of three things.<note place="margin">Three things.</note> Firſt, what are the termes required in the Covenant. Secondly, where in this Covenant conſiſts, or what is the ſubſtance of this Covenant. Thirdly, the reaſon why the Commandement is called a Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt of the termes required in the Covenant of us under the Goſpel. The tenure of the Law is in a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conſider<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion: Firſt, a legall performance of the Commandements. Secondly, an Evangelicall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance and obedience. Theſe are the two termes of conveyance of this Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The Law in the legall performance requires three things: that a man out of his perſonall holineſſe keepe it perfectly and exactly, and that to purchaſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111937:8"/>and obtaine life by this obedience. This is obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience according to the ſtrictneſſe and rigor of the Law, wherein it will not abate an haire of what God requires, but it muſt be fulfilled every jot, and that out of a mans owne perſonall holineſſe, and that in way of life: Thus it was a Covenant betweene God and <hi>Adam</hi> onely, <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocencie, God gave him a good Law, by vertue of which he ſhould have lived if he had kept it, and by that holineſſe he had by gift and creation he was able to keepe every mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nime and tittle of the precepts of the Lord, and to obtaine life thereby. But this Covenant is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued with us, is not required at our hands, no man doth or can performe the Law out of his owne holineſſe and goodneſſe exactly, to obtain life there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.24. <hi>We are not under the Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>but under Grace;</hi> that is, we are not bound to the ſtrictneſſe and rigour of the Law, that a man ſhould not live if he have in him any weakeneſſe and failings, therein we are free from the rigour, and curſe, and puniſhment of the Law. Secondly, Evangelicall obedience:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Law of God according to modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the mitigation of the Goſpel, ſo farre as God is pleaſed to accept of what we can doe through Chriſt in way of thankefulneſſe, not what we ſhould doe in regard of the exactneſſe God looks for at our hands, though we have no power of our own, we can not performe the Law exactly, yet if we according to the meaſure of grace received, walk in this obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence as well as we can in token of our thankfulneſſe; this is the tenure of the Covenant made with us.</p>
            <p>The ſecond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>art of the conveyance of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in it, take notice of three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, we have not power of ourſelves to keepe it:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111937:9"/>Secondly, we cannot perfectly performe it by that power we have: Thirdly, when we walke in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to it, we look not for life and ſalvation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. The ſcope of Evangelicall obedience, is to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God, and to expreſſe the Covenant by obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in way of thankfulneſſe, and to procure comfort to our ſoules. We are ſaved by the Covenant of faith, <hi>Beleeve and live, Ioh.</hi> 3.15.16.36. not, doe and live. This Covenant whereof we entreat, and whereof the Text is to be underſtood, is not the Covenant whereby we ſhall obtaine juſtification, but an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and ſigne, we are juſtified and accepted of God:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3.4. <hi>That which was impoſsible to the Law in that it was weake through the fleſh, God ſending his owne Sonne in the likeneſſe of ſinfull fleſh, and for ſinne, condemned ſinne in the fleſh: That which was impoſsible to the Law, &amp;c.</hi> that can never bring any man to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but onely Chriſt redeemed us fully, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied for us; and he performed what God required, and by that we ſtand juſt in the preſence of God. But being juſtified and made acceptable, the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, that we expreſſe the Covenant, and walke an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable unto it, &amp; expreſſe the vertues of him that hath called us. Brethren, you muſt not truſt to your new obedience, to expect life from it, it is onely an evidence that God hath ſhewed mercy to you; it makes not you good, but ſhewes that you are good. Evangelicall obedience according to the meaſure of grace received, is all that God lookes for: Not that there is worth in this to purchaſe ſalvation: It is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to us, that the Lord graciouſly looks upon us in Chriſt Ieſus; it is the way that we muſt walke in to ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Wherein doth this Covenant conſiſt?
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111937:9"/>It ſtands in three things: firſt, when in inward up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe and ſingleneſſe of heart, we labour to be caried in vertue of Gods command, not to doe what God requires onely, but becauſe God requires it: many of you come to the Church not becauſe God commands it; then you would not lie, or be drunke, or have ſecret baſe covetous humours, for God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands you ſhould not doe ſo, as well as he commands you ſhould come to the Church: If a command cary in any thing, it will cary in every thing. But the frame of an Evangelicall heart is to the Covenant: that is the ſpring of a mans practiſe, the firſt mover, the waight that makes him ſtrik in obedience to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Commandement, and approve inwardly of every Commandement of God; have not a ſecret diſtaſt of ſome, and a love of others: he is covetous to be drunke, but will not be covetous, covetous to come to Church, but will not humble his ſoule privately. Though many failings be in him, and many rubs and hubs in the way, yet the bent of his ſoule is to Gods Commandement. Caſt a Bowle, though there be a rub here, and hub there in the way which turne it out, yet it ſals upon the Bias: ſo an upright heart, though he meet with many hinderances within and without, yet the Bias of the ſoule, the bent is to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtill, to all his Commandements; labouring to expreſſe the vertues of God which hath called him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there muſt be an anſwerable expreſſion and putting forth of this inward diſpoſition, and frame of heart outwardly in tongue and life: If you had a good heart, you would have a good life, and a good tongue: If it be within, it will breake forth; you that are fretfull, proud, ſtubborne, peeviſh, ſtout,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111937:10"/>froward, and nothing but fiddle faddle, and lament it not; and thinke your heart is good, and you love the Commandements; you deceive your ſelves: If it were ſo, you would have a good tongue too, and be meeke and humble. I will not give a Ruſh for that man, Religion that is not in ſome meaſure obedient this way.<note place="margin">James 1.26.</note> What ſaith the Apoſtle? <hi>If any man ſeeme to be relig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous and r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne not his tongue, that mans Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is in vaine.</hi> There muſt be an expreſſion of the inward goodneſſe of the heart, by the outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ion: a good ſap in the botome, good b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anches and fruit on the lop.<note place="margin">Matth. 12.3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5.</note> 
               <hi>A good man out of the good trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his heart bringeth forth good things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If goodneſſe be in the heart (brethren) it will be brought forth in life: If ſuch bad ware be in the ſhop, there is as bad in the Warehouſe ſure, if not worſe. This we call the inward and outward Covenant; marke this you that thinke to ſmooth it over, and carry it away with faire lookes; and ſpeake well, and doe well outwardly, but have durty corners within: the heart is ſtubborne and rebellious againſt God; proud, ſtout, malicious, covetous: Theſe are in the outward Covenant, as thoſe whom the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of,<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Heare, O Heavens, and give eare, O Earth: for the Lord hath ſpoken, I have nouriſhed and brought up ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ldren, and they have rebelled againſt me.</hi> verſ. 3. <hi>The Oxe knoweth his owner, and the Aſſe his Maſters crib: but Iſrael doth not know, my people doth not conſider.</hi> The wicked are in Covenant with the Lord outwardly, but not inwardly; the heart cloſes not with God, they are not humble: The <hi>Iewes</hi> were Gods people in outward Covenant, but were diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and ſtubborne againſt the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:111937:10"/>
            <p>Thirdly, there muſt be an anſwering the means <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of Grace, with the meaſure of our uprightneſſe and obedience: He that hath received more, muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne more to God, brethren: He that hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved more helps from the Almightie, muſt returne more obedience; you know how Farmes and Leaſes goe, (brethren) he that hath a Leaſe of an hundred pound a yeere, muſt not goe and pay but fiftie pound. And he that hath one of fiftie pound, goe and pay but twenty pound; &amp; he that hath one of twenty pound, goe and pay but tenne pound; the Land-lord will not be put off ſo for his rent; anſwerable to the Leaſe, ſo muſt the rent be: you that live in this Congregation ſit at a high rate; brethren your Leaſes are at an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pound a yeere, looke that you pay God his full rent. The people that are in a Towne, that have a good honeſt Miniſter, and carefull and painefull; but he hath not thoſe abilities that another hath; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe not that diligent power, evidence of the Spirit in his Miniſtery; the people that are in ſuch a place, ſit at a good rate: but they that have a faithfull emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent powerfull Miniſter, they ſit at marvellous high rents. To pray little, and doe little in good duties, the Lord will not take this of a <hi>Dedham</hi> Chriſtian; that is for thoſe that have ſmall encouragements, and a Sermon now and then, and that but weake nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and creepe out once in a moneth to a Sermon, there is a fiftie pound rent, and a ten pound rent for ſuch to pay; but you ſit at an hundred pound rent, keepe touch, brethren, come off, come off currantly: Doe you thinke the Lord will lend his mercies for nothing? No, he prizes the life, libertie, and paines of his ſervants; and their prayers at an exceeding
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111937:11"/>high rate; an hundred pound for a Prayer, and an hundred thouſand for an Inſtruction: and doe you thinke with a prayer now and then, and with a ſigh, and a wiſh, that you could walke with the Lord, to poppe off the Lord ſo?</p>
            <p>No, you ſit at heavy rents, and the Lord will call for accounts accordingly at the day of reckoning: brethren, this will breake ſome of your necks, if it breake not your hearts now by repentance, for your being behinde hand with the Lord in his rent, and make you walke with the Lord better, and keepe touch with him for the time to come: But what is the reaſon that the Lord will call his Lawes and Commandements Covenants?<note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> The reaſon is this, for I would have nothing untouched that you may be wiſe and underſtanding Chriſtians, becauſe of the likeneſſe betweene, and the reſemblance of a Covenant that is made betweene two parties, and the Law, which is the Covenant which is given us of the Lord: In a Covenant, firſt there muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and Articles of agreement betweene the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties offered and conſented unto: and ſecondly, a binding one another to the performance thereof by Bond, perhaps a paire of Indentures are drawne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, wherein is declared, that they mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally agree; he to make good the land and to pay thus much rent: the other to let it him thus, and thus. It is juſt ſo here; Marke the agreement betweene us and the Lord:<note place="margin">Deut. 28. Levit. 26.</note> he propounds the Law, and ſaith, That if we will keepe the Law, he will bleſſe us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly in all things; houſe, and land, wife, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, at home, and abroad; in every thing we put our hand unto. Then the people they agree, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111937:11"/>ſay, Content Lord, what ever thou ſaiſt, we will doe;<note place="margin">Deut. 5.29.</note> the Law thou haſt given us, we will keepe it, it is holy, juſt, and good.</p>
            <p>But then for the binding of one another, you will ſay, How ſhall we know God will performe his part, and how ſhall the Lord know that we will performe our part to him, what Bond is there for it? The world is naught, and one cannot tell who to truſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God muſt binde us (brethren) to keepe our Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; and we are not to think much that he ſhould: And we have Bond of him too becauſe of our unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe: now the Bond is a corporall Oath paſſed from the one to the other. The Lord takes a corporall Oath, that if we will keepe his Commandements, he will not be God if he bleſſe us not: And ſo (bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) you ſweare too, again on the other ſide to the Lord, and did when you were baptized, every one of you, that you would be his people, and obey his Lawes and Commandements.</p>
            <p>The Lords people take a corporall Oath, and a Curſe upon themſelves, if they doe not keepe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with the Lord. This belongs to us at this day, for we entred into a Curſe, and deſired that all the plagues and curſes written in the Booke of God, might light upon us if we keepe not the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10. When the Lord had propounded the Covenant, marke how he deales with the people;<note place="margin">Deut. 29.10.</note> 
               <hi>You ſtand this day all of you before the Lord your God: your Captaines of your Tribes, your Elders, and your Officers, with all the men of Iſrael:</hi> verſ. 11. <hi>Your little ones, your wives, and the ſtranger that is in thy Campe, from the hewer of thy wood, unto the drawer of thy water:</hi> verſ. 12.<note place="margin">Deut. 29.12.</note> 
               <hi>That thou ſhouldeſt enter into Covenant
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111937:12"/>with the Lord thy God, and into his Oath</hi> (marke that brethren, the Oath of the Lord) <hi>which the Lord thy God maketh with thee this day:</hi> (marke that,) <hi>with us from Abraham to this day,</hi> the Oath is taken in our <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> we take the Oath of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> as it were, in this kinde; All you that have given your names to the Lord Jeſus, and have received grace from him, you all ſtand here this day before the Lord (and bring your childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before the Lord in the day of a Faſt, elſe woe be to you) that we may renew our Covenant with him. We are to enter into his Oath, the Oath of the Covenant betweene the Lord and us; that the Lord may ſtabliſh us to day for a People unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: and that we may curſe our ſelves, if we doe not walke with God, both our ſelves and ours: and woe to him that hath no care to keepe his Oath: no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he is a begger; no wonder his debtors run from him, and leave him in the lurch.</p>
            <p>It is a wonder that the earth doth not open her mouth and ſwallow him up,<note place="margin">Numb. 16.32.33.</note> as it did <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and all the plagues written from the beginning of <hi>Geneſis, to the end of the Revelation, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> fall not upon his ſoule and body. Why, you have entred into a curſe, man, and an Oath with the Lord, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 10.29.<note place="margin">Neh. 10.29.</note> See how the holy man continued this courſe, how they entred a Covenant there with the Lord; as if they ſhould have ſaid, The Lord curſe this tongue, if I ſpeake not graciouſly; the Lord curſe this hand, if I doe not yeeld obedience to his will and command: look to it, the curſe will dog thee, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thee, if thou break Covenant, as it did the <hi>Iewes,</hi> in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time: Now when he had returned the people out of captivitie, he brought them all before
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111937:12"/>the Lord, to enter into a Curſe, and into an Oath, to walke in Gods Law. It was a ſweet courſe; every ſoule here ſtands bound to doe as they did. They tooke a ſolemne Oath, what ever they had beene, they would now walke in Gods Law. Give me your hand, brethren, or at leaſt let me have your heart in the mean time, becauſe that cannot be. Are you the ſervants of God, entred into Covenant with the Lord? then know you are bound to keepe Covenant by vertue of that Oath; and when you are in your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, remember your Oath; you are bound hand and foot to the Lord, and therefore when you are drawne by any thing to breake Covenant with the Lord, thinke thus with your ſelves: What, an honeſt man and lie, and forſweare my ſelfe? you have all ſworne to the Lord, brethren, your little ones and all. Curſed ſhall you be in all that you take in hand, if you doe not walke preciſely, and exactly in his Law and Covenant Husbands, call upon your wives,<note place="margin">Husband and Wiſe.</note> and Parents, call upon your children, when you ſee them breake Covenant; and ſay, Wife, or children, What, ſhall we bring a Curſe upon our ſelves? When you begin to be careleſſe of the Sabbath, and cold, and luke-warme, and dull; call upon one another, and ſay, You know the plague was neere at hand, husband at ſuch a time; but the Lord kept it from us. For Gods ſake husband, let us take heed that we doe not bring the curſe upon our Family: No marvell though one runne away with this from us, and an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with that; and the Lord lay this ſickneſſe, and that affliction upon us: What, wilt thou be a perjured man? for ſhame keepe thy Oath; God will never truſt thee elſe hereafter.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:111937:13"/>
            <p>Now the Lord ſweares to us by himſelfe,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.13.</note> becauſe he hath no greater to ſweare by. It is a ſweet thing that the Lord hath bound himſelfe by Oath to us, to keepe Covenant with us. If you have an honeſt and an able man bound to you for a debt, you goe away content, you have enough: Why, we have the Lord in bonds, for the fulfilling his part of the Covenant: He hath taken a corporall Oath of it, that he will doe it; and ſhall we not take the Lords bond, and reſt content with that? Let us now<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 13.22.</note> 
               <hi>ſuffer the words of exhortation,</hi> with patience and meekneſſe; O bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, this point concerns us neerely this day. Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants goe farre, eſpecially if they be for weighty matters; when a man is in Covenant for more then he is worth. Thinke of it ſeriouſly.</p>
            <p>The firſt uſe ſhall be of Examination.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 1.</note> If this be ſo, we may have a touch-ſtone from the forme of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine delivered, to diſcover to us, who is the ſound profeſſor indeed: There are a great many formall profeſſors, but few true ones indeed. A man can ſcarce tell who to truſt, you ſay, for trading; I ſay, for living; you ſay, for buying and ſelling; I ſay, for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing: Would you know whether you are ſound at root, and not have a name onely <hi>to live, and yet are dead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3. verſ. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.1. Let him that keeps Covenant, that deales ſquarely, (you know what that is brethren) that keeps touch with the Lord, let him be the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere man, he is worthy the name of a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>There are many fadling patching Chriſtians, that are off and on; here and there; there is no hold of them; a man knowes not where to have them; that will ſay faire, and bid well, but doe nothing in the end. Goe you home to your ſelves, ſee whether you
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111937:13"/>keepe touch with the Lord. You thinke you are bound to keepe covenant in nothing but in your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; Rich men thinke all honeſty is in paying of money.</p>
            <p>I will not ſpeake of the miſery of them that muſt patch up and down in that faſhion, and hang on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry buſh; But (ô ſayes the rich man, that is carefull to give every man their due, and to keepe his day) what times doe we live in, a man knows not where to lend to have it againe at his time, there is no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt dealing to be found; Marke the villany of his heart, becauſe he keepe touch with men, and is as good as his word; O ſayes he, we live in very ill times, and their is ſcarſe a man to be found, that one may truſt of his word, there is ſuch unhoneſt dealing in all places, that there is no hold of mens words: But yet oppreſſes and grindes the face of the poore, and looks for his gaine altogether: where is your honeſty? So ſome that are carefull of the body, and give it its due, but the ſoule whines within for mercy, mercy that it may have ſomething to refreſh it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but that cannot be heard, that is ſtarved, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is fat, but the poore ſoule is leane enough: where is your honeſty? doe you not owe repentance, hearing, reading, and praying to your ſoules? your poore ſoule crys, ô remember me, let me have ſome mercy and forgiveneſſe ſought for me at the hands of the Lord, let me have ſome time imployed for my good; But you cannot heare it; Is this honeſty brethren? if a man ſterve his ſervant, ſo that he pine away, till he is ſcarſe able to goe, and at laſt come to the grave, every one cryes out ſhame of him; But ô brethren, the poore ſoule that is ſtarved; but no man cryes ſhame
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111937:14"/>of that, when did the Lord heare of many of you here preſent? Alas, never brethren, never; But when the ſoule ſaid, now pray for helpe againſt this corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and for mercy for ſuch a ſin, now awake out of thy ſecret worldlineſſe; you went away and would not heare that, you have no leiſure nor no time for that, but ſtarve your poore ſoule, and the devill he hath one part of your time, and your luſts another; Is this honeſty brethren? This is the man God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemes as an honeſt man, not a Proteſtant at large, that hath a good purſe, and is good in his kinde, and will deale honeſtly with men, and pay them their due, and at their day, but he that will pay God and their ſoule their due too:<note place="margin">Exod. 19.5.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.5. <hi>If you will obey my voyce indeed and keepe my covenant, then you ſhall be a peculiar treaſure unto me;</hi> If your debtors keepe day with you, you will trade with them rather then with any other man. Let it be ſo in your dealings with men, but remember that you do it with God. Think not to put off the Lord with faire ſpeeches; Good words pay no debts, Brethren; we come here, and give the Miniſter hearing, and God a gloſing; but we walke not according to Gods commandements. You give God good words, but you goe home, and are as unprofitable as vaine, and frothy, and idle, as ever you were. If one owe you money, and take this day, and that day, and promiſe it, and not pay it; you would not thinke well of this dealing; what may the Lord thinke of your hearts, when you have made ſo many promiſes to him, and had ſo many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions to performe your part of the covenant to him, but have not yet kept promiſe with him? Good words are good in their kinde, God likes them well,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111937:14"/>as it is in <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.28, 29. <hi>This people have ſaid well;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 5.28.</note> 
               <hi>but theſe</hi> are not ſufficient, we have enough of this ſayes the Lord; <hi>O that there were ſuch an heart in them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 19.</note> 
               <hi>to doe as they have ſaid!</hi> There is the point Brethren. If we have a debtor that comes oft to us, and promiſeth us payment, but keeps not day, we ſay, you give me good words, but I cannot pay debts ſo, and keepe my family ſo; Where is my money? So Brethren, you come and heare cheerefully, and pretend that you will doe that you heare? Ah, but give God his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; <hi>O that there were ſuch an heart:</hi> Know what God cals for; Good money: will he be payd with counters and ſhews? No, but currant money of England, when the heart is changed, the ſoule turned, and the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions moved to what God cals for, and that is good, equall and righteous, and we deſire with all our heart to performe it.</p>
            <p>Brethren, when you are gotten home, call to minde what you have ſaid this day, and this covenant: which you have entred into with the Lord, and ſay, ô Lord that I had ſuch an heart: good words are well, but ô a heart, a heart Lord is that which thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireſt, and I would have; And it muſt be alwayes, and in all things, you muſt not picke and chuſe, and ſay, I will not be a drunkard, yet be covetous: I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that you will not game, and be drunke, and yet gripe the poore; O that there were an heart to keepe the commandements of God alwayes;<note place="margin">1 Sam. 13.14. Act. 13.22.</note> This is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man with God, a man after Gods own heart, a man of Gods minde as we may ſay. If ever there were a Saint, thou art: when the Lord ſayes, O that they had ſuch an heart, the heart anſwers and ſayes, O Lord that I had ſuch an heart; when the Lord ſayes,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111937:15"/>O that thou wouldeſt keep all my commandements: O that I could, ſayes the ſoule againe. This is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right faire dealing indeed, currant money, your tongue and outward appearance is nothing, that ſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and peeviſh heart let it be humbled, and your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward and rebellious heart be brought into ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:<note place="margin">Tit. 2.9.</note> And you ſervants, not anſwer your maſters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; And you little ones be not ſturdy againſt your parents, and diſobedient unto their commands; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the little ones that mocked <hi>Eliſha.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 2. 23, 24.</note> O but you will ſay, we cannot doe what we would. No, it is pitty you ſhould, for then ſome of you would be without ſin, which cannot be here. But doe you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to doe what you can, and are you humbled and grieved for that you cannot doe, and doe you ſtrive towards perfection, and ſay with <hi>David, Thou haſt</hi> commanded that I ſhould <hi>keepe thy ſtatutes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.4.</note> O that I could Lord;<note place="margin">Verſ. 5.</note> 
               <hi>O that my wayes were directed to keepe thy ſtatutes.</hi> And doeſt labour to mend thy pace, becauſe thou haſt been ſlow, and art caſt behind in the way to happineſſe, and haſt loſt thy time? This is all God requires of thee. If one that is in debt to you, fall into decay, and come to you and ſay he is not able to pay you your money, but he deſires you to goe to his houſe, and take whatſoever is there, that is worth any thing, to ſatisfie you; I appeale to your conſciences, is he not an honeſt dealer? yes, you will not deny it, but you will pitty his caſe and ſay, the Lord may croſſe any man, and you will be favourable unto him, becauſe he ſhews an honeſt minde, in that he deſires every man ſhould have his own to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt he can, either in money or in money worth. So brethren, obſerve what the ſoul wants in obedience,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111937:15"/>that it may plucke it out in repentance, that is the money worth, that when the poore ſinner finds a dead heart, a ſluggiſh indeavour, weakneſſe in perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and he cannot doe as he ſhould doe, yet what he wants in obedience, he fetcheth out in repentance, ſtep but in at the entry doore, or under the wall, or under the window, and heare how he will breake his heart, bewaile his abominations, cry out of himſelfe and ſay, though much means and grace have been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered me, yet good Lord this wretched world, that I ſhould dote upon <hi>lying vanities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jon. 2.8.</note> ſo as to <hi>forſake mine own mercies;</hi> Good Lord, ſubdue this earthly minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; Good Lord take all away rather, then this ſhould take my ſoule from thee and from happineſſe.</p>
            <p>O thus brethren, he labours to pleaſe the Lord, in ſorrow and griefe, and mourning, for the ſhort com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of his payment in obedience. He lays load upon himſelfe in this caſe. This is an honeſt heart; this is very good pay, it is money or money worth, he is humbled, and aſhamed, and confounded, becauſe he cannot doe what he would; In this caſe he deals ſquarely, he is an honeſt Chriſtian; An honeſt man, if he be caſt backe in his eſtate, he will intreat Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his creditors, and reſolve and promiſe them too, that if ever God make him able his family ſhall not gaine by it, but he will pay them to the utmoſt farthing, ſo is it with an honeſt heart brethren.</p>
            <p>I looke not that a man ſhould not have temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and corruptions, and that ſometime prevailing over him, but this thou muſt have, and thus thou beg earneſtly of the Lord, godly ſorrow and griefe of heart for thy failings, and that he would recover thy <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 39.13.</note>ſtrength before thou goe from hence and be no
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111937:16"/>more: Though thou looſe this weeke, that thou maiſt gather it up the next weeke, worke ſo much the more, and the harder. The Lord be mercifull to us, where are thoſe honeſt men to be found brethren, that deſire to doe thus? Me thinke I heare you in your ſouls now ſaying, good Lord what will become of our towne, good Lord what will become of our neighbours? they talke of honeſty, and this is hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty; but alas, their life agrees not to it. You com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of trading in the world, almoſt no truſt to be put in any, every man almoſt is turned banckrupt: I am ſure brethren it is true in Religion; He that was a forward Chriſtian a while agoe, is a drunkard now, or a gameſter now; And he that was a forward Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour, and would goe to a Sermon foure or five mile in a morning, and come home againe, and to worke hard to get up the time againe; But now God hath given him a pretty eſtate in this world, he is turned a very muck-worme, become covetous, or a looſe one; Though I doe not know you brethren, I am ſure brethren, there are a number ſuch abroad in this land, and I doubt not but you can point at ſuch here in this congregation, and ſay, that is ſuch a man, and that is ſuch a man, he ſtill ſeeks to hold in with his Miniſter and would faine be counted a Profeſſour, but O there is no life, nor heart, nor power of godlineſſe in him, he is grown ſtarke cold ſince I knew him, the world hath a part of his heart, his pleaſure another, his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit another, idleneſſe and eaſe another, he may even lay the key under the threſhold, for any found Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and true grace indeed, he is quite downe the winde. But you will ſay, haply that I thinke too hardly of you: I know you not, I hope brethren there
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111937:16"/>are many of you godly; the Lord increaſe your num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and his graces that are in you: but I am ſure if you come to the ballance, you ſhall finde few that are ſound and godly Chriſtians indeed that will hold weight.</p>
            <p>Let us ſearch a little; Why, you will ſay, I hope we are honeſt men the moſt of us, we pay every man his due; It is well you doe ſo, but I will bring in a bill now brethren, which if you cannot prove to be cancelled, woe be to you.</p>
            <p>This Doctrin caſts out aboundance in all places,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> at this doore, and at that doore, and packs them out, and will leave poore thin congregations. We will ſcan the caſe a little brethren.</p>
            <p>Firſt, hence it is cleare, that the poore ignorant creature is gone, he is quite blown up if he ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, he knows nothing in this kinde, he knows not how to count twentie ſhillings, how ſhall he ſatisfie a debt of twentie pound? that is to ſay, brethren, they know not God, not underſtand the prayers that they make, they ſay the Lords <hi>Prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lords Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note> and it is good to be uſed in its time, but doe you pleaſe God in ſo doing, when you underſtand not what you ſay? one ſayes, <hi>Hallowed be thy Name;</hi> when he knows not what Gods name is, and what it is to hallow it. Another ſayes, <hi>Thy Kingdome come,</hi> when he knows not what it is to have his kingdome come; You cannot count your money yet, you cannot diſcerne a ſix pence from a groat, that is to ſay brethren, you know not what it is to pray, and to heare the word, you know not what it is to take the Name of God reverently into your mouthes. And ſo ſome will call God Father, but they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111937:17"/>know not how he is their Father, nor how they come to be his children. Theſe are gone, they are carnall, they have not pay, therefore certainly cannot pay the Lord his due.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is another generation worſe then theſe, and thoſe are profane ones, that ſet themſelves pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly to run to rerages with the Lord, ſcorne all means God hath appointed to bring in his debts by, they will be drunke, ſweare, profane the Sabbath, ſcoffe at ſuch as <hi>refraine their foot from evill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 59.15.</note> Tell them God requires other things of them, &amp; that they keep not touch with him, and he expects other things at their hands, and that they run in rerages with the Lord for his rent, and that he will arreſt them, and confound them, if they doe not pay him his rent, for the time to come; They ſay they purpoſe no other payment then he hath already at their hands, but let God get his own as he can, they will take their own courſe ſtill; Is there any ſuch here brethren? There are too many ſuch in the world, and I feare too, ſome among you, though you pretend faire, and ſay not ſo openly, yet you ſay ſo by your deeds brethren; for you will have this privy haunt, and that ſecret evill way, take this and that wicked courſe, you reſolve of it, and will doe it, let the Lord get his own if he can. So he will I warrant you, Looke to it you that think to brave it with the Lord, when you are among your cups and companions, and to make your part good with him, to out-brave all judgements, and who ſhall arreſt you; the Lord will plucke the cup out of thy hands and arreſt thee with death, and a thouſand de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils ſhall lay hold on thee, and drag thee to hell to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111937:17"/>thee for ever. God will have his rent one way or other. Thinke of it you that ſet your mouthes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt heaven, and what hath the Miniſter to doe to ſpeake againſt you, you will out face God, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Goſpell and all, and thinke to goe away ſcot-free. Looke to it, God will get his own, he will have it of thee, as he had it out of <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate. I will all edge but one place to you for this purpoſe, and that is <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.18. the Text ſayes,<note place="margin">Deut. 29.18.</note> 
               <hi>That if there be any root of bitterneſſe among them,</hi> verſ. 19.<note place="margin">Verſ. 19.</note> 
               <hi>That when he heareth the curſe of the Lord, ſhall yet bleſſe himſelfe in his heart,</hi> ſaying, he ſhall eſcape and doe well enough for all that; The Text ſayes,<note place="margin">Verſ. 20.</note> 
               <hi>That the wrath of the Lord ſhall ſmoake againſt that man, and he ſhall blot out his name from under heaven.</hi> Oh that this verſe were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed upon the palme of the hand of every drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, and every ſcoffer, and profane one, that walks after the ſtubbornneſſe of his own heart, <hi>and addes drunkenneſſe to thirſt,</hi> and yet you thinke to goe away with it, and ſo you may for a time, and theſe words breake no bones, and all this winde ſhakes no corne with you, you hope to goe to heaven as well as the beſt, you will drinke and whore and yet it ſhall go well with you in the end, and you are proud; and ſtout, and ſtubborn, and ſtiffe-necked againſt the Lord, and the voyce of his word, and yet you bleſſe your ſelves, and promiſe to your ſelves peace.</p>
            <p>Marke what the God of Heaven ſaith,<note place="margin">Verſ. 20.</note> 
               <hi>The anger of the Lord ſhall ſmoke against that man, and all the curſes that are written in this Booke, ſhall lie upon him, and the Lord ſhall blot out his name from under Heaven.</hi> verſ. 21.<note place="margin">Verſ. 21.</note> 
               <hi>And the Lord ſhall ſeparate him unto evill out of all the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111937:18"/>Tribes of Iſrael:</hi> All the vengeance of the Almighty that ever was made knowne, ſhall light upon the head and heart of that drunkard, and that contemner of God, and the word of his Grace. <hi>He will ſeparate you from the Tribes of Iſrael.</hi> You thinke to run away from your Countrey, and to flie from his Judgements, as ſome Bankerupts do eſcape from men, to run to <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> and other places: No, <hi>the Lord will ſeparate that man from all the Tribes of Iſrael;</hi> where ever he be, in <hi>France, Germany, Amſterdam,</hi> or where ever; he will ſeparate him, and ſet the damned ſpirits on the backe of him, and ſay, Take hold of that man, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute vengeance on him.</p>
            <p>Brethren, you may think I deale ſomething harſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with you, but I deale for the beſt for you: Is it not better to heare of this now in time, then hereafter, when the Lord hath arreſted you, and you are locked up in cloſe priſon for ever; you ſhould thinke, Oh if ſuch a denunciation had beene told me; if ſuch an exhortation had beene wrought upon me; if ſuch a man had preſſed hard upon my conſcience, with ſuch and ſuch things, I had never come here. Conſider this, God will have it out of you, as he had it out of <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> that had blaſphemed Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the field, an arrow came from God and ſmote him that he died; and then he ſaid, Thou haſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come me, <hi>O thou Galilean.</hi> You that are mates in this kinde, goe home to your fellow drunkards, and to your fellow whoremaſters, and ſcoffers, and thoſe that ſide with you againſt God and goodneſſe and ſuch as are godly, and tell them, God will have his debt of them. Know it now to your humiliation, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111937:18"/>amendment, leſt you know it to your coſt, when there will be no prevailing with the Lord for mercy. The Lord perſwade your hearts that there is no way to eſcape, but by coming in and acknowledging your debt, and craving pardon though you cannot pay.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the cloſe hearted Hypocrite,<note place="margin">Vſe <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> he comes here to be diſcarded; he thinkes his penny good ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, &amp; the world eſteems of him as a ſincere, honeſt, upright hearted man. Tell him that he keeps not Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with the Lord, he takes it in great indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If any be here (as this Age begetteth a world of cloſe hypocrites) underſtand and know, if you keep back ſome of the payment, have a ſecret haunt; doe as <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> did,<note place="margin">Acts 5.2.</note> that laid downe a part of the price, for which the poſſeſſion was ſold, and ſaid,<note place="margin">Verſ. 8.</note> It was all: Is here all, ſaith <hi>Peter</hi> to them? Yes, all, ſaith he; ſo when the Lord ſaith to you, Doſt thou pray? Yes, Lord: And doſt hate all ſinne? Yes Lord, ſay you: Why doſt lye to the Almighty?<note place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note> Doe you not know a company of ſecret haunts, and back-dores that you have, to this luſt, and that luſt; and many ſecret corruptions you have; and yet come into the preſence of the Lord, as if you were upright with the Lord, and there were no ſuch matter. O ye hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, why hath Satan filled your hearts <hi>to lye to the Lord?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note> Doe you not know what <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid to <hi>Gehazi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 5.20.21.</note> when he ran after <hi>Naaman</hi> for a bribe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. <hi>Where haſt thou been, Gehazi? Thy ſervant hath been no where:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 25.</note> he thought to waſh it away, and make it over ſo with a lye, <hi>verſ.</hi> 26.<note place="margin">Verſ 26.</note> 
               <hi>Went not mine heart with thee</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eliſha</hi>) <hi>when thou ranneſt after Naaman</hi> for a bribe? If any cloſe hypocrite be in the Congregation, let him
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111937:19"/>know, the Lord will finde him out; and will ſay to him, Whither went thy heart all this while? Where haſt beene dodging? Was not my heart with thee, <hi>verſ.</hi> 26. when thou wenteſt after ſuch a ſecret haunt, and ſuch a cloſe luſt? O but you will ſay, it is no ſuch matter, you deſire to be upright; I ſay, be ſo, brethren. The Lord goes with thee wither ſo ever thou goeſt, and he ſees all thy <hi>Dalilahs,</hi> and <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaſſes</hi> of pride, and ſelfe-love; he ſeeth how thou ſeekeſt to him in the pride of thy heart; and how thou profeſſeſt to get a name, and to bold in with others. Theſe are baſe abominations, curſed hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie: this is falſe-heartedneſſe before God, and ſhall be plagued by God at the day of account. There is not an honeſt woman, that hath but one other man beſides her husband. He is not an honeſt man that will not pay one bond of tenne, or many. A penny is due as well as a pound. My hand is on your heart, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, for I feare many of you have ſome one back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore which you meane to keepe; and you will be proud or covetous a little; or uncleane onely, and all the reſt of that Covenant ye are content to keepe: Is this honeſt, to ſcrape out what you pleaſe, and leave what you pleaſe ſtill? there is no honeſtie in this, brethren; But you will ſay, Who can lay any thing to my charge? I ſay, thou art a Covenant-breaker, and the Lord could never get his owne of thee yet: Well, yet thou wilt put it off, as <hi>Saul</hi> did, when <hi>Samuel</hi> came to meet him, as he returned from ſlaying the <hi>Amalekites;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.13.</note> 
               <hi>Come thou bleſſed of the Lord.</hi> But what ſaid <hi>Samuel</hi> to him?<note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> Ah, ſaies he, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>What meanes the bleating of the ſheepe, and the lowing of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111937:19"/>the Oxen?</hi> So you ſay, you make conſcience of all the Commandements of the Lord; But what meane theſe ſecret corners and haunts? I mean thoſe which conſcience and God heare of, not what I heare of; for I know nothing but by them: What meane all theſe ſecret conveyances, that you have to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and hide your luſts with, that you may live in them and not be knowne ſo to doe? What meanes your drunkenneſſe in a corner; your adultery in a corner; your hypocriſie, and covetouſneſſe; luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmeneſſe, and coldneſſe; careleſneſſe, and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mindedneſſe?</p>
            <p>Yet men will not be out-faced, they will beare a man downe ſtill, that it is ſo. Then I have no other way but this with you; looke what a man doth by a debtor, that ſaith the debt is paid, and will face him downe that it is ſo; yet the Booke is not croſſed: What will this Creditor do now? Why then, to your Bookes he goes, and cals in the ſervant, that takes in the reckonings, and ſaith, Doe you remember it? No, ſaith the ſervant, you gave me good words di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times, when I called on you for it, but no money was paid: why then I never had it. So brethren, you ſay, that you are holy; we will call for the Bookes, and for Conſcience, Gods Auditor, and the keeper of his accounts, and aske that; Whether you make conſcience of private prayer, and humbling your ſoul in ſecret? Whether you make conſcience of your ſtubborneſſe to your husband; of your peeviſhneſſe and untowardneſſe? Whether you be a Covenant-keeper, and whether you did ever performe that God hath required of you; he hath required much
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111937:20"/>of you, that you ſhould pray, read, be ſober, humble, neeke, dutifull to your husband. But you have been right, froward, undutifull, way-ward; why, did you pay this debt to the Lord then?</p>
            <p>The conſcience will ſay, No Lord; I urged him to it, and ſaid, Now get alone<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa, 26.16.</note> and powre out a prayer to the Lord; now goe and read, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on the word of God; and I told him, Lord, when he began to be ſo eager of the world, now you will be covetous, and worldly; but he would not heare me; he promiſed me, Lord, he would leave it, and would doe ſo no more; and he would take up this duty and that duty; and put me off this time, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other time, but he never did it. Then you ſee the caſe cleere, for you never kept day; you have a ſhew of godlineſſe,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.5.</note> but where is the power of it? The power is to ſubdue inward luſts, ſecret corruptions, baſe thoughts that riſe in the minde. This is not to be found in the moſt; therefore they are but Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites and falſe hearted. At laſt when the caſe is ſo cleare by the Booke of the ſervant, this bad debt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor doth confeſſe it, and ſaith, It was a hard time, and it was but little, if you had had it, I thought it could doe you no great good, I hoped you would have bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed it, if you had had any great need of it. So ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a cruſed hypocrite confeſſes the converſation is good, and the courſe is holy which he ſhould take, and which God requires of him; but I feared the loſſe of my libertie, of my eaſe, or my honor, and credite, if I had done it. I feared I ſhould have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for it, and it was but this, I hope it was not ſuch a matter. Is this honeſtie, when God and the Goſpel,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111937:20"/>call for truth, and for ſinceritie, you put off and ſay, This is no great matte, you hope; there are worſe matters then ſo in the world. Thou art no upright, God will have the utmoſt farthing;<note place="margin">Mat. 5.26.</note> there is truth in a penny. He that will not ſuffer in one kinde, I will never beleeve he will ſuffer in another. But you will ſay, What if a man be covetous, he hurts none; it is his owne that he holds ſo faſt; he is but cloſe fiſted a little, I hope this is not ſuch a matter? This is a great ſinne brethren, in ſuch a place as this is; what, not keepe touch here? that mans ſinne that lives under the Goſpel, is the greateſt ſin of all; of more weight then the ſinnes of any beſides: and therefore looke to it brethren. If a man forfeit a Bond of twenty pound, or forty pound, perhaps he may recover it; but if of forty thouſand pound, we ſay it will cruſh the greateſt Merchant in the Land, and breake his back. An hypocrite, a falſe-hearted one in the place where the Goſpel is; it is a heinous foule ſinne, it will ſinke him deepe: A drunkard where the Goſpel is not, and an adulterer where the Goſpel is not, ſhall goe to hell; they ſhall all periſh without repentance. But he that lives under the means, ye is covetous, looſe, proud, vaine, oppreſſing, and griping of his poore brethren; worldly, or the like; that Bond will break thy backe, it is an hundred thouſand pound Bond. Take heede, brethren, a man that runs in arerages with the Lord here, it will be heavy for him.<note place="margin">Mat. 11.23.</note> 
               <hi>And thou Capernaum, which wert lifted up to heaven, ſhalt be caſt downe to hell.</hi> Some live at great rents. A <hi>Ded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> man, God will not have him have a ſtomacke onely to a good duty, and now and then to pray, or
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111937:21"/>to reade, or conferre; but he requires great debts of him: A <hi>Dedham</hi> drunkard, or hypocrite, careleſſe carnall Goſpeller, or covetous one; the devils will rejoyce for him; when he comes to hell; they will make Bonefires, and make it holiday for him, ſtand upon their tiptoes to look on him, and ſay, What, are you come hither after all Prayers, and Sermons, and Sacraments, and Admonitions; and ſo many labors of Gods ſervants, that have worne out their lives to keepe you from hence?</p>
            <p>This Bond will breake your backe brethren, an hundred thouſand millions worth of exhortations you have had, and you owe the Lord for them all ſtil; you have paid him nothing for them yet; you are not one whit the better for them: What ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of you? the Lord will ſet a thouſand devils to torment you, when you drop into the pit: ſpecially ancient men, woe to your ſoules, if once God lay hold of you: If a man that is in debt, for I know not how many Bonds, be arreſted but upon one, it will caſt him into priſon; but then if after that comes another, and another, in upon him, it will goe very hard with him. He plaid faſt and looſe, and faire, and farre off all this while; but now one hath clapt a Writ upon his backe, comes another and arreſts him for an hundred pound at ſuch a mans ſuite; and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other arreſts him for an hundred pound at ſuch a mans ſuite. O thinke of this, your reckonings will be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full when God caſts you on your ſicke bed, and death comes to fetch away your ſoules, and you are going to the chaines of darkneſſe; then there will come in one Bond after another, upon you; one inditement
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:111937:21"/>after another againſt you: <hi>Item,</hi> for the ſinnes of your youth; your diſobedience and ſtubborneſſe to Parents, and Governours, when a childe: <hi>Item,</hi> for following your profits, and pleaſures, and minding nothing elſe, when you were a young man: <hi>Item,</hi> for your worldlineſſe ſince you were an old man. One Bond after another the Lord will lay upon you. You would thinke ſuch a man that hath ſo many Bonds come upon him, in a hard caſe; quite undone; and that there is no recovery for him out of priſon, but there he muſt lie till ſome part of him rot off, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, and till he die in the Jayle: O how you would pitie ſuch a mans caſe, and how you would be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for him! But O brethren, you that are husbands, or wives, or parents, when you ſee your children, or your husbands arreſted by God; not to goe to an earthly Jayle, but to goe to hell for ever! O how ſhould it grieve your ſoules for ſuch a one! how ſhould you pitie ſuch, and deſire the Lord, while there is helpe and hope, to ſhew mercy upon them!</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee theſe three ſorts are caſhiered for not being ſound; and the Lord be mercifull unto us,<note place="margin">Vſe <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> what a few are there beſides theſe? Thinke of this, cary it home with you, and examining your ſelves, know the Lord will have ſinceritie from you.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is a word of conſolation;<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> this is a marvellous comfort to thoſe that love and feare the Lord: all you whoſe hearts anſwer, It is thus with you, lift up your heads with joy, for this will uphold you, and make you<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 21.28.</note> lift up your heads with comfort in all your troubles, and in the day of the Lord, <hi>When
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111937:22"/>your redemption draweth nigh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 3.10.</note> Iſa. 3.10. ſay, <hi>It ſhall goe well with the godly.</hi> I ſay to that man, what ever come, it ſhall goe well with him. We uſe to ſay, without doubt, without danger. A man that owes nothing, he cares not for any Purſevant, or Sergeant, or Baily; he feares them not, for he knowes they have nothing to doe with him: This is a marvellous comfort to him; ſo it ought to be to a ſincere heart, that hath paid his debt to God, when trouble ſeiſes upon him: you know what <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">2 King. 20.3.</note> 
               <hi>Good Lord remember, how I have walked before thee with an upright heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 38.3.</note> If a man be arreſted upon a falſe ground, the Law will baile him; there is no Law againſt him: Thinke of that brethren,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.21.</note> 
               <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.22. <hi>The fruits of the Spirit are love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Verſ. 23.</note> 
               <hi>meekeneſſe, temperance; againſt ſuch there is no Law.</hi> There is no Law to puniſh or condemne them, or accuſe them. Therefore bleſſed are your ſoules, that are ſincere and upright in heart &amp; converſation alwaies, to all Gods Commandements; in publique, in private; in ordinarie times, and extraordinarie; there is no law againſt you: whatſoever Satan, or the world ſay againſt you, there is no law in the Booke of God to condemne you.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.6.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6. <hi>Then ſhall I not be confounded when I have reſpect to all thy Commandements.</hi> In the times of all dangers, and of all miſeries, which are like to ſeiſe upon us ſoone, if the Land ſhould be over-run, and friends and means faile, here is comfort to every faithfull ſoule, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.15. <hi>All fleſh is graſſe,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 103.15.</note> 
               <hi>the winde paſſeth over it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 16.</note> 
               <hi>and it is gone.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 17.</note> ver. 17. <hi>but the loving kindneſſe of the Lord
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:111937:22"/>endures for ever, and ever.</hi> Upon whom, brethren? <hi>Vpon them that feare him, and thinke upon his covenants, to doe them.</hi> Marke how he ſuſtaines himſelfe, life goe, friends goe, meanes goe; <hi>all fleſh is graſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note> 
               <hi>the winde paſſeth over it, and it is gone;</hi> meanes are gone, how then, brethren? <hi>verſ.</hi> 17.<note place="margin">Verſ. 17.</note> 
               <hi>But the goodneſſe of the Lord endures for ever and ever.</hi> Though Libertie be gone, the Spirit of the Lord endures; though means be gone, the mercy of God endures;<note place="margin">Pſal. 136. all.</note> though friends be gone, the favour of the Lord endures: <hi>The loving kindneſſe of the Lord endures for ever;</hi> Upon whom? <hi>upon them that feare him, and thinke upon his Covenants to doe them.</hi> Though a poore ſoule fare meanly, and live hardly; all helps gone, the Winde hath paſſed over them; and libertie is gone; honour is gone; life is going; nothing endures: yet lift up thy ſoule in ſickneſſe, and ſay, My health is gone; my ſtrength is gone; my life is going; <hi>but the loving kindneſſe of the Lord endures for ever,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 18.</note> 
               <hi>upon every ſoule that keepes his Commandements, and thinks upon his Covenants to doe them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, for a word of exhortation;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 4.</note> Is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God his Covenant; and is the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that, the way to obtaine mercy and happineſſe here, and for ever? then goe away if you will, and be diſhoneſt ſtill, and breake Covenant with the Lord. The very name of diſhoneſtie, me thinks, ſhould move you, brethren, to be faithfull in your Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and to ſet on ſpeedily, and to be exceeding watchfull, and carefull; and to performe what you have promiſed to the Lord. Reaſon ſhould move
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:111937:23"/>you; What, not keepe Covenant, eſpecially with the Lord? What, ſhall we make promiſes to the Lord, and enter into Covenant with him, and not keep it? Let it for ſhame never be ſaid of us, brethren. Marke what <hi>David</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119 11.</note> 
               <hi>I have hid thy Commandements in my heart, that I might not ſinne againſt thee.</hi> His minde ran of them, and his tongue talked of them conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually. Amongſt men, brethren, you would not have your credit cracked for any thing; and you doe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly. A good name is a Jewell. But doe thus with the Lord, brethren; Hath not the Lord kept touch with you, in all his promiſes? Did you ever beg any thing of him, and he not heare you? Why doe you not keepe touch with the Lord? Shame your ſelves for this, I beſeech you. Men in the world, if they breake in their eſtates, they have this love and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie in them, that if any loſe, then it ſhall be they that did deale moſt hardly with them; and that got moſt by them when they were in trading; but this kinde friend, that was kinde to him, and lent him monie ſometime in his need, he ſhall not loſe a penny by him: O, ſaith he, I had a friend of him, I could never come to him, but he would receive me. This is honeſtie, and faire, and equall: O conſider of this, brethren; we have hard bargains at the hands of the world, and of the devill, and ſinne; many knocks of ſoule, and girds of conſcience with them: But the Lord hath beene ever gracious, mercifull, loving, and kinde to us: reſolve therefore that the Lord ſhall never loſe by you; let the world loſe if it will; and let carnall friends, and ſinne, and Satan loſe if they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:111937:23"/>will: Let not the Lord loſe; but reſolve, what ever becomes of it; I will pray conſtantly, and reade in my family morning and evening; and upon every occaſion, and reforme my waies. It is not needfull that I ſhould be rich; it is that I be ſincere, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the Lord: I will labour for a good conſcience, and endevour to walke with God.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur: <hi>Ja. Cranford.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
